Guide to the Records of the National Jewish Welfare Board, undated, 1889-1995 (bulk 1917-1990) *I-337
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
- Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers, undated, 1904-1995 (bulk 1920-1980); 919 linear feet.
  - Series B: Field Services, undated, 1911-1995 (bulk 1921-1980); 371 linear feet.
    - Subseries 6: Regional Area Offices, undated, 1911-1995 (bulk 1945-1975); 169 linear feet.
      The files document activities within JWB's regional areas. There are no files for the Southern Section (which was formed in 1944), though the Atlanta Office files do cover activities at JCCs and Ys in the South. (The Federation files include a small amount of material on the early years of the Southern Section.) Atlanta, Charleston, Chattanooga, Dallas, Fort Worth, Memphis, New Orleans, and San Antonio are particularly strongly represented. Of particular note is the 1972 study of Jewish youth of Birmingham, Alabama. The material is arranged alphabetically by city, though some field reports are also collected in "Southern Section, JWB Field Reports." (Some other parts of the country are also included in the Atlanta Office files.)
      The Boston Office files pertain to the Institute for Jewish Life, which later became the Jewish Media Service. The documents reflect the Media Service's efforts regarding the effective use of media in Jewish education and in cultivating Jewish life in the United States. Included are evaluations of films made available through the Media Service, as well as information on institutions which rented the films. Some files on specific topics, such as Soviet Jewry, can also be found here. (For related material, see Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series A: Program Services/Subseries 5: Jewish Media Service.) The Denver Office material provides information on activities in the Western Area. Of note are the files on USO Activities and teen conferences. Also included here are documents maintained by Herman Markowitz, who served as director of Western Services from 1971 to 1978; this material consists of files on JCCs and Ys in the U.S. and Canada. The Federation files chronicle the early years of Federations throughout the country. Items of note include issues of New York Federation News and (in the files on the Metropolitan Association of Jewish Center Workers) a 1943 seminar on a postwar agenda.
      The Pennsylvania Federation of YMHAs held its first convention in 1910. In the 1920s, this Federation merged with the newly formed Middle Atlantic States Federation, and later became the Middle Atlantic Section of JWB.19 Of particular note in the Middle Atlantic files are the History files which include programs for the 1919, 1922, and 1925 section conventions, as well as constitutions and bylaws, and JCC objectives and statements of purpose. The Subject Files include annual reports, executive board minutes from 1923 to 1970 (there are no minutes from 1956 to 1965) and a statement of principles regarding Center-Federation relationships. Also included in the Subject Files are programming resources for the centenary of Jewish chaplaincy and materials on the merger of the Middle Atlantic Section and the 2nd Army Services Committee. In addition, files Arthur Brodkin maintained in his role as community consultant can also be found here. These files document Bodkin's involvement in the Mid-Atlantic Council, as well as his role in Biennial preparation and Health & Physical Education activities.
      The Midwest Section was founded in 1939 and was admitted into JWB the following year.20 The documents collected here consist of Community and Subject Files. The Subject Files include a study of Federation and Center Executives regarding their views of the American Jewish community, and also contain a variety of conference materials. Information on the Midwest section's 1963 and 1965 Biennials can be found here. Also included is material on the Centenary Committee; this includes a compilation of articles and speeches from various years, recounting events in JCC's development and history.
      The Scrapbook Files include bylaws and constitutions of the Midwest section. Some material on Canada is included in the Community files, and a photograph of the first five Midwest Area presidents is located in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup.
      The New England Area files document activities in the New England region, including the actions of Alfred Dobrof and Leonard Katowitz, regional and community consultants. Included in the Administrative Subject Files are house policies, consisting of rules and guidelines for various JCCs, and work plans for the New England area. The History Files include dedication journals and studies of New England communities, while the Minutes Files include a program of the first annual convention of the Associated Ys of New England-the New England Section's predecessor-in 1911, as well as programs for other meetings up to 1952. Materials on the third to fifty-ninth New England annual conventions can be found in the Proceedings files, while the Subject files include New England constitutions and further material on conventions. (The 1954 convention file includes letters from the governors of Virginia, Maine, Rhode Island, Connecticut, New Hampshire, Maryland, Delaware, and Pennsylvania.) Also of note is a 1912 YMHA convention photograph, with signatures of the New England Region's board on the back; this can be found in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup.
      The New Jersey Federation of YMHAs was established in 1912 and joined JWB in 1921. About half of the New Jersey Area material consists of community files, documenting JCC and Y activities from 1966 to 1983. (Some files on New York, Connecticut, and Canada are included in the files of Jack Boeko, community consultant.) Of note in the Subject Files are the work plans of Mitchell Jaffe, consultant to the New Jersey Area and Assistant Director of Community Services, and Al Dobrof, New Jersey Consultant. Subject files also include a variety of material on Nursery School Institutes, Teen Activities, Health and Physical Education, and meetings of JCC and Y executives. Also of note is the JWB Study Committee material, which describes a proposed reorganization of JWB structure.
      The Metropolitan League of YMHAs and Kindred Associations, formed in 1913, was reorganized as the New York Metropolitan Section-Jewish Welfare Board in 1936. It served as the planning, activating, coordinating and servicing agency for Jewish Community Centers and kindred organizations in the five boroughs and neighboring parts of Westchester and Long Island.21 Almost half this subseries consists of files of the Metropolitan Section: included are the papers of Harold Arian, who was appointed Administrative Field Secretary in 1954 and served in that capacity until 1971. His files consist of journals (the Journal of Jewish Communal Service and Jewish Social Service Quarterly) and Subject Files. Of note in Arian's Subject Files are the materials on the Bronx Y Study and the Bronx Y Golden Age Club, and the 1966 Teen Workers conference, which includes material on the values of middle class Jewish teenagers.
      Articles of Incorporation, Constitutions, By-Laws and Financial Statements for the Metropolitan section can also be found here. (Some financial statements for JWB itself are also included.) Of particular note is the material on the Hunts Point project, which was initiated in the spring of 1934, as part of an experimental effort to reduce delinquency among Jewish youth. In addition, this section includes a 1946 survey of the New York City Jewish population's cultural and recreational needs, and files on JCCs and Ys in the various boroughs of the city. (These files are collected under Organizations and also under City Wide and National Agencies.) Over half of the New York Metropolitan material consists of Subject Files, the bulk of which fall between 1941 and 1981. Items of note in the Subject Files include the History File, in the "1954" subject file and the Historical material in the Alphabetical Subject Files, which include constitutions and bylaws for the Metropolitan League of Ys and Kindred Associations, as well as the Metropolitan League of JCAs and other associations. Some reel-to-reel and audiotapes can be found in the Audio Visual Materials Subgroup.
      The New York State Section was first organized in 1915, as the New York State Federation of YMHAs, and joined JWB in 1921. The New York State material consists of Subject Files and the files of Herman Sainer, who became Administrative Regional Consultant in 1964. (Much of the material maintained by Sainer actually precedes this appointment.) Of note are the documents on the Administration on Aging, and the files on New York cities and towns. Some material from Arthur Brodkin's tenure as Field Secretary is included in the Subject Files. (Brodkin was appointed in 1961.) The Phoenix Office files consist of the records of George Korobkin, director of Western Services. This material is primarily administrative in nature.
      The Washington DC Office files document the work of that office, which focused on services to JWB, JCCs, and Armed Services. These services included public affairs, program and administrative services, representation of JWB to local and national meetings and federal departments and agencies and direction of the Government Division Campaign for United Jewish Appeal of Greater Washington.22 Included here are June Rogul's files on JCCs. (Rogul served as director of the Washington Office.) Also included are community files documenting visits to Virginia JCCs conducted by Moe Hoffman in his capacity as Regional Consultant, and Subject Files, which include personal services files dealing with court martials in the 1960s.
      In 1936, eleven societies on the West Coast organized the Pacific Coast Federation of Jewish Community Centers, which was admitted into JWB two years later and became the Western States Section.23 Included here are the files of George Korobkin, who served as director of Western Services. (Additional Korobkin files can be found in the Phoenix Office material, and further information on the Western area can be found in the Denver Office files.) The Western Area material consists primarily of Community and Subject Files. The bulk of the Community Files concern Canada and the Western states, though some other states are also included. Of particular note is the material on the 1980s Kansas City Study, which assessed the JCC's adult education, fine arts, theater, jazz, poetry, early education, and humanities programs.
      The subseries includes correspondence, field reports, meeting minutes, brochures, reports, news clippings, surveys, journals, work plans, studies, personnel profiles, certificates, constitutions, by-laws, publications, photographs, audio-tapes, (located in the Audio-Visual Materials subgroup), maps, charts, posters, and blueprints (located in the Oversized Materials subgroup.)
      19 Change and Challenge: A History of 50 Years of JWB. Page 14. Janowsky, Oscar I., Louis Kraft, Bernard Postal. New York: National Jewish Welfare Board. 1966
      20 Change and Challenge: A History of 50 Years of JWB. Page 15. Janowsky, Oscar I., Louis Kraft, Bernard Postal. New York: National Jewish Welfare Board, 1966
      21 New York Metropolitan Section-JWB - Its Functions. 1955, I-337, NJWB. American Jewish Historical Society
      22 JWB Today: Part I Services, Facilities, Staff JWB Today: A Guide and a Directory, Part I Services Facilities Staff, New York: JWB, 1947
      23 Change and Challenge: A History of 50 Years of JWB. page 15. Janowsky, Oscar I., Louis Kraft, Bernard Postal. New York: National Jewish Welfare Board, 1966
      Related Materials: Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series A: Program Services/Subseries 3: Health and Physical Education; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series A: Program Services/Subseries 5: Jewish Media Service; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 3: Field Reports; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 4: Geographic Files; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 5: Regional Area Files.
      Restrictions: Several files are restricted due to fragility or subject matter. Boxes are marked accordingly.
  - Series C: Public Relations, undated, 1917-1988 (bulk 1925-1969, 1981-1987); 72 linear feet.
    This series is divided into two subseries: 1) Department of Communications and 2) Public Information Services.
    The Public Relations Department assisted JWB in maintaining its position as the leadership and central service agency of North American JCCs and YM-YWHAs. The Department helped to create and transmit JWB's messages to its constituents, thus fulfilling JWB's role as advocate for a united JCC movement. The Department served as JWB's liaison with the American Jewish and general press and also published the JWB Circle, which showcased the work of JWB, the Center movement, and individual JCCs. In addition, the Department provided JCCs, Centers, and Federations with a variety of publications, and evaluated the JCCs' own public relations material. The Department also consulted with local agencies, to assist them with their public relations efforts and promoted Jewish educational and cultural programming in JCCs.24
    24 "JWB Communications and Public Relations," undated, I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
    - Subseries 1: Department of Communications, undated, 1967-1988 (bulk 1981-1987); 22 linear feet.
      General Correspondence (undated, 1918, 1952, 1967-1988; bulk 1981-1987), Press Releases and Projects (1981-1983). Arranged chronologically (general correspondence) and numerically (press releases and projects.)
      The Department of Communications sought to promote a positive image of JWB as the headquarters for the Association of Jewish Community Centers and YM-YWHAs in North America and as the sponsoring agency for the Lecture Bureau, Jewish Music and Book Councils, Jewish Media Service, Armed Forces and Veterans' Services Committee, and Commission on Jewish Chaplaincy.25
      This material consists of General Correspondence files, and Press Releases. The General Correspondence includes work plans for Frank Wundohl, Director of Communications and Public Interpretation, and Lionel Koppman, Director of Public Information Services and Executive Editor of the JWB Circle. Also included are files on staff member projects, copies of the JWB Circle, and information on JWB's Book Council, the Rockower awards, the American Jewish Press Association, JWB Biennials, and Israel.
      In addition, material on the Commission on Maximizing Jewish Educational Effectiveness and its Implementation Committee can be found here. (For more material on this, see the Jewish Education Programs sub-series.) Also included are departmental materials such as personnel files and a speech delivered by President Ronald Reagan at the Bergen-Belsen American Israel Public Affairs Committee. The press releases document JWB activities, as well as staff appointments and JWB award winners. Several video and audiotapes were moved to the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup and a wide assortment of photographs, including photos of JWB staff members with Golda Meir and Israeli Foreign Minister Abba Eban, can also be found there. Other materials include reports and news clippings.
      25 "Department of Communications and Public Interpretation Work Plan & Goals. October 1982-August 1984," October 1982, I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
      Related Materials: Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series E: Jewish Education programs/Subseries 2: Commission on Maximizing Jewish Educational Effectiveness.
      Restrictions: personal data, Frank Wundohl, 1981; Applicants, 1982; Personnel, Grotte, Rita & Personnel, Thomas, Patrice, 1983
    - Subseries 2: Public Information Services, undated, 1916-1986 (bulk 1925-1969); 50 linear feet.
      Artwork (undated), Biennial (1966, 1970-1972, 1983-1986; bulk 1966, 1972, 1986), Biographical Files (undated, 1930-1982), General Files (undated, 1917-1984; bulk 1941-1984), Golden Jubilee (1966), Jewish Community Center Services (undated, 1945-1971), Lionel Koppman Files (undated, 1938-1986), Photographs: General and Historical Documents (1916-1970), Arnulf Pins Files (undated, 1940-1954), Bernard Postal Files (undated, 1917-1918, 1927-1969, 1978-1982; bulk 1940-1960), Press Releases and Clippings (1969-1970,1976-1977, 1981-1982), Printing Plates (circa 1919-1922), Publications (undated, 1923, 1926, 1930s-1983; bulk 1950-1975) Mainly arranged alphabetically. (General Files are chronological, Lionel Koppman files and Press Releases are chronological and numerical.)
      The Department of Public Information promoted broader community understanding of the role of JCCs and also provided individual centers with technical public relations assistance and guidance.26 The duties of the director of Public Information Services included serving as the Executive Editor of JWB Circle and also researching and writing press releases on JWB/JCC activities, such as the Jewish Media Service and Lecture Bureau.27 The files collected here reflect JWB's efforts in this area and consist of correspondence, meeting materials, reports, printing plates, art work, certificates, speeches, surveys, pamphlets, fact sheets, art work, conference proceedings, biographies, contest entry forms, articles, press releases, news clippings, annual reports, yearbooks, newsletters, bulletins, bound volumes, (located in Subgroup VI: Oversized Materials), photographs, videotapes, film reels, audio-tapes, and slides (located in Subgroup V: Audio-Visual Materials).
      Some Biennial files are included here, as are some biographical files on individuals of note, such as Yitzhak Rabin, Sandy Koufax, Jack Dempsey, General Douglas MacArthur, Eleanor Roosevelt and Hank Greenberg. Biographical information on some JWB staff members is also included.) These files consist mainly of clippings and photographs, with the photographs located in Subgroup V: Audio-Visual Materials. Materials of note in the General Files include some files on anti-Semitism and a 1944 speech by Massachusetts Representative James Curley and a signed letter from him. In addition, material on a radio program called "We the Guilty" can be found here, as can an index to the first two volumes of the JWB Circle and a 1949 pamphlet entitled "JWB Today" which describes the services JWB offered at that time. Other materials on note include some pencil drawings by Feingold, as well as printing plates for army and navy certificates. The Photographs: General and Historical Documents material includes Photostats of letters to JWB from Presidents Theodore and Franklin Roosevelt, Woodrow Wilson, Harry Truman, Lyndon Johnson and John F. Kennedy. (This material was found with the historical photographs located in Subgroup V: Audio-Visual Materials)
      The files of Lionel Koppman, who became head of Public Information Services in 1970, include entry forms for JWB's Communications Awards competition, which honored public relations professionals working in a variety of communications media.28 (Related material can be found in the Audio-Visual Material series.) Entries were submitted by synagogues, JCCs, YM and YWHAs, camps, and VA chapels. The files of Arnulf Pins, in his capacity as chair of the National Jewish Youth Planning Commission can also be found here. Also of note are a wide variety of publications documenting activities at the national, regional, and local levels of JWB. Included here are annual and semi annual reports, position statements on various issues, meeting minutes, and newsletters, newspapers, and bulletins. (Bound volumes of the JWB Circle, dating from 1949 to 1965, can be found in the Oversized Materials Subgroup.)
      Finally, about a third of this material consists of the files of Bernard Postal, who became director of Public Information in 1946 and remained in that position until 1970. The bulk of the Postal material consists of General Files and Press Releases; some material on military heroes and Jewish families with more than one child serving in World War II is also included, as are some files on the Committee to Reappraise Public Understanding of JWB. Postal's General Files cover an extremely wide range of topics, from fascism and anti-Semitism in such countries as England, Germany, Czechoslovakia and Canada to the Boy Scouts. Files on individuals such as novelist Pearl Buck, Supreme Court Justice Black, actress Claire Bloom, and President Franklin D. Roosevelt are also included here, as are files on the Emergency Committee to save the Jews of Europe and a National Conference of Christians and Jews. A copy of the World War I High Holy Days Prayer book can also be found in Postal's General Files.
      Several boxes of photographs have been removed from these files and added to the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup.
      26 JWB Today: A Guide and a Directory. Part I Services Facilities Staff; Part II The JWB Family. Page 28. New York: National Jewish Welfare Board, 1947
      27 "Work Plan - 1983/1984. Director of Public Information Services." I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society
      28 "JWB Communications and Public Relations," undated, I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
      Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governance/Series D: Conventions and Committees/Subseries 1: JWB Biennial Conventions; Audio-Visual Material Subgroup.
  - Series D: Personnel Recruitment and Training, undated, 1917-1987 (bulk 1945-1975); 87 linear feet.
    This series contains one subseries: Personnel Services.
    This series documents the recruitment and training efforts of JWB's personnel department, which served as the main source of professional staff for JCCs and camps. The department interviewed applicants, evaluated workers and served as a resource to JCC leaders on personnel problems, in addition to organizing training institutes to enrich the professional skills of center workers.29
    29 JWB Today: A Guide and a Directory. Part I Services Facilities Staff. New York: National Jewish Welfare Board, 1947
    - Subseries 1: Personnel Services, undated, 1917-1987 (bulk 1945-1975); 87 linear feet.
      This subseries is divided as follows: Bessie Pine files (undated, 1969-1973), Edward Kagen files (undated, 1971-1987), General Files (1968-1977), Israel Program Resource Materials: Irving Brickman files (undated, 1948, 1955, 1958-1974; bulk 1969-1972), JWB Organizational Files (1954-1975; bulk 1959-1973), JWB Personnel Files (1925-1935, 1938-1942; bulk 1938-1941), Personnel Data: Clerical Employees and Support Staff (1942-1985; bulk 1950-1972), Personnel Evaluations (1941-1962), Personnel Profiles: Scholarships (1964-1969), Personnel Profiles: Sets A, B and C (undated, 1918-1972; bulk 1942-1963), Professional Personnel Records (1917-1983; bulk 1940-1960), Reference Material (undated, 1944, 1956-1971), Scholarship Material (1957-1970), Scholarship Rejections (1971-1976), Sherwood Epstein files (undated, 1951-1974; bulk 1969-1974), Solomon Greenfield files (undated, 1948, 1958-1987; bulk 1976-1986), Staff Training (undated, 1944-1975; bulk 1966-1975), [Executive] Training (1969-1978), Training Services (undated, 1935-1971; bulk 1965-1970), and USO Employee Cards (1921-1970; bulk 1941-1947). Arranged alphabetically.